Clouds.
السحب
Have you ever noticed how much people moan about them?
هل لاحظتم كيف يتذمر الناس منها؟
They get a bad rap.
تتمتع السحب بسمعة سيئة.
If you think about it, the English language
لو تأملتم الأمر، فإن اللغة الإنجليزية
has written into it negative associations towards the clouds.
جعلت للسحب ارتباطات ذهنية سلبية في كتاباتها.
Someone who's down or depressed,
فعندما يشعر الشخص بالاكتئاب أو الإحباط
they're under a cloud.
فيشار إليه بكونه تحت السحب.
And when there's bad news in store,
وعند وجود أخبار سيئة ،
there's a cloud on the horizon.
نقول هناك سحب تلوح في الأفق.
I saw an article the other day.
رأيت مقالاً منذ بضعة أيام.
It was about problems with computer processing
كان حول مشاكل معالجة الكومبيوتر للمعلومات
over the Internet.
على الإنترنت.
"A cloud over the cloud," was the headline.
وكان العنوان: "سحابة فوق سحابة أخرى."
It seems like they're everyone's default
تبدو السحب وكأنها التعبيرالافتراضي
doom-and-gloom metaphor.
للهم والغم عند الجميع
But I think they're beautiful, don't you?
ولكنني أعتقد أن السحب جميلة، أليس كذلك؟
It's just that their beauty is missed
فقط لم يتنبه أحد لجمالها
because they're so omnipresent,
لأنها منتشرة في كل مكان،
so, I don't know, commonplace,
إذن، لا أدري، أمر مألوف
that people don't notice them.
لا يلحظه الناس.
They don't notice the beauty, but they don't even notice the clouds
إنهم لا ينتبهون إلى جمالها ، ولا يمكنهم حتى ملاحظة السُحب
unless they get in the way of the sun.
إلا إذا اعترضت طريق الشمس
And so people think of clouds as
ولهذا ترتبط السحب عند الناس بفكرة
things that get in the way.
كونها أشياء تعترض الطريق.
They think of them as the annoying, frustrating obstructions,
فهم يعتبرونها مجرد عراقيل مزعجة ومحبطة،
and then they rush off and do some blue-sky thinking.
ومن ثم يندفعون لتأمل السماء الزرقاء.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But most people, when you stop to ask them,
ولكن معظم الناس، عندما تسألهم،
will admit to harboring a strange sort of fondness for clouds.
سيعترفون بنوع من الولع الغريب للسحب.
It's like a nostalgic fondness,
وكأنه ولع الحنين
and they make them think of their youth.
فالسحب تذكرهم بشبابهم
Who here can't remember thinking, well,
من منكم لا يتذكر، حسنا،
looking and finding shapes in the clouds
كيف كان يتأمل السحب ويجد أشكالا
when they were kids?
عندما كان طفلاً،
You know, when you were masters of daydreaming?
حسنا، عندما كنتم بارعين في أحلام اليقظة؟
Aristophanes, the ancient Greek playwright,
أريستوفانيس، الكاتب المسرحي اليوناني القديم،
he described the clouds as the patron godesses
وصف السحب بأنها الآلهة الراعية
of idle fellows
للرفاق العاطلين عن العمل
two and a half thousand years ago,
قبل 2500 عام
and you can see what he means.
ويمكنكم فهم ما كان يرمي إليه.
to allow ourselves the indulgence
لأن نسمح لأنفسنا بالانغماس
of just allowing our imaginations
وإطلاق العنان لخيالنا
to drift along in the breeze, and I think that's a pity.
للانجراف مع النسيم، وأعتقد أن هذا أمر مؤسف.
I think we should perhaps do a bit more of it.
أعتقد ربما ينبغي لنا أن نفعل هذا بصورة أكبر.
I think we should be a bit more willing, perhaps,
أعتقد أننا يجب أن نكون اكثر رغبة نوعًا ما،
to look at the beautiful sight of the sunlight bursting out
في النظر إلى المشهد الجميل عندما ينبعث ضوء الشمس
from behind the clouds and go, "Wait a minute,
من وراء السحب ويختفي، ولكن لننتظر لحظة،
that's two cats dancing the salsa!"
أليست هاتان قطتان ترقصان السالسا؟
(Laughter) (Applause)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
Or seeing the big, white, puffy one up there
أو رؤية تلك السحابة الكبيرة المنتفخة بأعلى هناك
over the shopping center looks like
فوق مركز التسوق تبدو كأنها
the Abominable Snowman going to rob a bank.
رجل ثلجي بغيض على وشك السطو على مصرف.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They're like nature's version of those inkblot images,
إنهم بمثابة نسخة طبيعية لصور بقع الحبر،
you know, that shrinks used to show their patients
تلك التي كان يعرضها الأطباء النفسيون على مرضاهم
in the '60s,
في الستينات
and I think if you consider the shapes you see in the clouds,
وأعتقد أنكم لو أمعنتم النظر في الأشكال التي ترونها في السحب،
you'll save money on psychoanalysis bills.
يمكنكم توفير المال الذي تدفعونه للمحللين النفسيين.
Let's say you're in love. All right?
حسناً، فلنفترض أنك مولع بشخصٍ ما
And you look up and what do you see?
ونظرت إلى السماء، فماذا ترى؟
Right? Or maybe the opposite.
صحيح؟ أو ربما العكس.
You've just been dumped by your partner,
قد تكون منفصلاً للتو عن شريكك
and everywhere you look, it's kissing couples.
وفي كل مكان تنظر إليه ترى أزواجاً يتبادلون القبل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Perhaps you're having a moment of existential angst.
ربما تمر بلحظة قلق وجودي.
You know, you're thinking about your own mortality.
حسناً، أنت تفكر في لحظة وفاتك.
And there, on the horizon, it's the Grim Reaper.
وهناك، في الأفق، يلوح لك قابض الأرواح.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Or maybe you see a topless sunbather.
أو قد ترى فتاة تتشمس عارية الصدر.
What would that mean?
ماذا يعني ذلك؟
What would that mean? I have no idea.
ماذا يعني ذلك؟ ليس لدى أدنى فكرة.
But one thing I do know is this:
ولكن ما أعرفه حقاً هو:
The bad press that clouds get is totally unfair.
الانتقاد اللاذع للسحب ليس عادلاً على الإطلاق.
I think we should stand up for them,
وأعتقد أنه ينبغي علينا أن ندافع عنها،
which is why, a few years ago,
ولهذا، وقبل بضع سنوات
I started the Cloud Appreciation Society.
أنشأت ما يسمى ب "جمعية تقدير السحب".
Tens of thousands of members now
أصبح لدينا عشرات الآلاف من الأعضاء الآن
in almost 100 countries around the world.
في ما يقرب من 100 دولة في جميع أنحاء العالم.
And all these photographs that I'm showing,
وجميع هذه الصور المعروضة أمامكم
they were sent in by members.
قد قام الأعضاء بإرسالها.
And the society exists to remind people of this:
والجمعية موجودة لتذكير الناس بالفكرة التالية:
Clouds are not something to moan about.
السحب ليست أمرًا ينبغي أن يتذمر الناس منه.
Far from it. They are, in fact,
على العكس، فهي في الواقع،
the most diverse, evocative, poetic aspect of nature.
من أكثر جوانب الطبيعة تنوعًا وشاعرية وإثارةً للعواطف
I think, if you live with your head in the clouds
أعتقد أن تأمل السحب
every now and then, it helps you keep your feet on the ground.
بين الحين والآخر، يساعد على المحافظة على الهدوء والاستقرار.
And I want to show you why, with the help of
وأود أن أوضح لكم السبب بمساعدة
some of my favorite types of clouds.
بعض أنواعي المفضلة من السحب.
Let's start with this one. It's the cirrus cloud,
دعونا نبدأ مع هذه، وهي سحابة القزع،
named after the Latin for a lock of hair.
وهي كلمة لاتينية معناها خصلة شعر.
It's composed entirely of ice crystals
تتكون بالكامل من بلورات ثلجية
cascading from the upper reaches of the troposphere,
تتساقط من الطبقات العليا من التروبوسفير،
and as these ice crystals fall,
وعند وقوع هذه البلورات الثلجية،
they pass through different layers with different winds
تمر عبر طبقات مختلفة ورياح مختلفة
and they speed up and slow down,
تتسارع وتتباطأ
giving the cloud these brush-stroked appearances,
مما يعطي السحابة هذا المظهر الشبيه بضربة الفرشاة،
these brush-stroke forms known as fall streaks.
وتعرف هذه الأشكال الشبيهة بضربة الفرشاة بالخطوط المتساقطة.
And these winds up there can be very, very fierce.
وهذه الرياح الموجودة بأعلى يمكن أن تكون عنيفة جداً.
They can be 200 miles an hour, 300 miles an hour.
يمكن أن تبلغ سرعتها 200 كم في الساعة، أو 300 ميل في الساعة.
These clouds are bombing along,
تمر هذه السحب بانفجارات،
but from all the way down here,
ولكن هنا من أسفل،
they appear to be moving gracefully, slowly,
تبدو وكأنها تتحرك برشاقة وبطء،
like most clouds.
مثل معظم السحب.
And so to tune into the clouds is to slow down,
إن الالتفات إلى السحب يعني التأني،
to calm down.
والهدوء.
It's like a bit of everyday meditation.
فهو بمثابة قليل من التأمل اليومي.
Those are common clouds.
هذه سحب عادية.
What about rarer ones, like the lenticularis,
وماذا عن السحب الأكثر ندرة، مثل السحب العدسية ؟
the UFO-shaped lenticularis cloud?
السحابة العدسية الشبيهة بالجسم الطائر مجهول الهوية
These clouds form in the region of mountains.
تتكون هذه السحب في منطقة الجبال.
When the wind passes, rises to pass over the mountain,
عند مرور الريح، ترتفع لتمر فوق الجبل
it can take on a wave-like path in the lee of the peak,
بإمكانها أخذ مسار تموجي في الجانب المحمي من الريح عند القمة،
with these clouds hovering at the crest
مع تلك السحب المحلقة على قمة
of these invisible standing waves of air,
هذه الموجات الهوائية الثابتة غير المرئية
these flying saucer-like forms,
هذه الأشكال الشبيهة بالصحن الطائر
and some of the early black-and-white UFO photos
وبعض الصور القديمة بالأبيض والأسود للأجسام الطائرة مجهولة الهوية
are in fact lenticularis clouds. It's true.
هي في الواقع سحب عدسية، هذا صحيح.
A little rarer are the fallstreak holes. All right?
و سحب الثقوب هي أقل ندرة . حسنًا؟
This is when a layer is made up of very, very cold
ويحدث هذا عندما تتكون طبقة من قطرات المياه
water droplets, and in one region they start to freeze,
شديدة البرودة وتبدأ في التجمد في منطقة معينة
and this freezing sets off a chain reaction which spreads outwards
ويتسبب هذا التجمد في انطلاق سلسلة تفاعلات تنتشر نحو الخارج
with the ice crystals cascading and falling down below,
مما يتسبب في تساقط بلورات الثلج إلى أسفل
giving the appearance of jellyfish tendrils down below.
وإعطاء مظهر قنديل البحر المحلاق من أسفل.
Rarer still, the Kelvin–Helmholtz cloud.
تعتبر سحابة كيلفين هلمولتز من السحب الأكثر ندرة.
Not a very snappy name. Needs a rebrand.
ليس اسمًا أنيقًا فهو يحتاج إلى إعادة تسمية
This looks like a series of breaking waves,
تبدو هذه وكأنها سلسلة من الأمواج الكاسرة،
and it's caused by shearing winds -- the wind
والسبب في ذلك هو الرياح الكاسرة
above the cloud layer and below the cloud layer
إن الرياح الموجودة أعلى طبقة السحب وأسفلها
differ significantly, and in the middle, in between,
تختلف اختلافًا كبيرًا، وفي الوسط وما بينهما
you get this undulating of the air,
تجد هذا التموج الهوائي
and if the difference in those speeds is just right,
وإذا كان الفرق بين هذه السرعات هو الفرق المطلوب ،
the tops of the undulations curl over
تلتف قمم هذه التموجات
in these beautiful breaking wave-like vortices.
مشكلةً هذه الدوامات الجميلة التي تشبه الأمواج.
All right. Those are rarer clouds than the cirrus,
حسنًا. هذه السحب أكثر ندرة من سحب القزع ،
but they're not that rare.
ولكنها ليست نادرة إلى هذه الدرجة
If you look up, and you pay attention to the sky,
إذا نظرت لأعلى وانتبهت إلى السماء
you'll see them sooner or later,
ستشاهدها عاجلاً أم آجلاً،
maybe not quite as dramatic as these, but you'll see them.
ربما هي ليست مثيرة مثل تلك، ولكنك ستراها.
And you'll see them around where you live.
وسوف تراها في المكان الذي تعيش فيه.
Clouds are the most egalitarian
السحب هي أكثر عروض الطبيعة تكافؤًا
of nature's displays, because we all have a good,
لأننا جميعًا لدينا
fantastic view of the sky.
منظر رائع للسماء.
And these clouds, these rarer clouds,
وهذه السحب، هذه السحب الأكثر ندرة،
remind us that the exotic can be found in the everyday.
تذكرنا بأنه يمكننا العثور على أشياء الغريبة في حياتنا اليومية.
Nothing is more nourishing, more stimulating
لا شيء أكثر تغذية أو أكثر تحفيزًا
to an active, inquiring mind than being surprised,
للعقل النشط المتحقق من المفاجأة والدهشة
being amazed. It's why we're all here at TED, right?
ولهذا نحن جميعًا هنا في تيد TED، أليس كذلك؟
But you don't need to rush off
ولكنك لست في حاجة إلى ترك المألوف
away from the familiar, across the world
والسفر حول العالم
to be surprised.
للتتفاجأ
You just need to step outside,
أنت فقط بحاجة إلى الخروج،
pay attention to what's so commonplace, so everyday,
والاهتمام بما هو مألوف وموجود بشكل يومي
so mundane that everybody else misses it.
وعادي لدرجة أن الجميع لا يلحظه.
One cloud that people rarely miss is this one:
إحدى السحب التي نادرًا ما تفوتنا هي
the cumulonimbus storm cloud.
السحابة الركامية المصحوبة بالعواصف.
It's what's produces thunder and lightning and hail.
وهي التي ينتج عنها الرعد والبرق والمطر الثلجي.
These clouds spread out at the top in this enormous
تنتشر هذه السحب بأعلى بطريقة
anvil fashion stretching 10 miles up into the atmosphere.
هائلة وشكل يشبه السندان ممتدة ً لمسافة 10 أميال أعلى الغلاف الجوي
They are an expression of the majestic architecture
وهي تعبر عن الفن المعماري المهيب
of our atmosphere.
الذي يمتاز به الغلاف الجوي.
But from down below, they are the embodiment
ولكن في الأسفل فهي تجسد
of the powerful, elemental force and power
القوة الجبارة والأولية
that drives our atmosphere.
التي تتحكم في غلافنا الجوي.
To be there is to be connected in the driving rain
إن وجودها يعني التواصل مع الأمطار
and the hail, to feel connected to our atmosphere.
والأمطار الثلجية والشعور بالتواصل مع غلافنا الجوي
It's to be reminded that we are creatures
لنتذكر أننا مخلوقات
that inhabit this ocean of air.
نسكن هذا المحيط من الهواء
We don't live beneath the sky. We live within it.
نحن لا نعيش تحت السماء، بل نعيش بداخلها.
And that connection, that visceral connection to our atmosphere
وهذا الارتباط، هذا الارتباط بيننا وبين غلافنا الجوي
feels to me like an antidote.
أراه بمثابة ترياق.
It's an antidote to the growing tendency we have
ترياق لميلنا المتزايد نحو
to feel that we can really ever experience life
الشعور بأننا يمكننا حقًا خوض تجربة الحياة
by watching it on a computer screen, you know,
بمشاهدتها على شاشة الحاسوب، أعني
when we're in a wi-fi zone.
عندما نكون في منطقة بها شبكة واي فاي
But the one cloud that best expresses
لكن السحابة التي تعطينا أفضل توضيح عن سبب
why cloudspotting is more valuable today than ever
كون مشاهدة السحب أكثر نفعًا الآن من أي وقت مضى
is this one, the cumulus cloud.
هي هذه السحابة، السحابة الركامية.
Right? It forms on a sunny day.
أليس كذلك؟ وهي تظهر في الأيام المشمسة.
If you close your eyes and think of a cloud,
إذا أغمضت عينيك وفكرت في السحب
it's probably one of these that comes to mind.
على الأرجح سيتبادر إلى ذهنك واحدة من هذه السحب.
All those cloud shapes at the beginning,
جميع هذه الأشكال من السحب كانت في البداية
those were cumulus clouds.
سحب ركامية
The sharp, crisp outlines of this formation
إن الخطوط الحادة والهشة التي يتميز بها تكوين هذه السحب
make it the best one for finding shapes in.
يجعلها الأفضل لاكتشاف الأشكال
And it reminds us
وتذكرنا بأن مشاهدة السحب
of the aimless nature of cloudspotting,
تتميز بكونها بلا هدف
what an aimless activity it is.
يا له من نشاط لا هدف له
You're not going to change the world
لن تغير العالم
by lying on your back and gazing up at the sky, are you?
بالاستلقاء على ظهرك والنظر إلى السماء، أليس كذلك؟
It's pointless. It's a pointless activity,
فهو أمر لا معنى له ونشاط عبثي
which is precisely why it's so important.
وهو أمر هام للغاية لهذا السبب تحديدًا
The digital world conspires to make us feel
يتآمر العالم الرقمي ليجعلنا نشعر
eternally busy, perpetually busy.
بأننا مشغولون إلى ما لا نهاية، مشغولون دائمًا
You know, when you're not dealing with
تعلمون، عندما لا تتعامل مع
the traditional pressures of earning a living
الضغوط التقليدية بسبب كسب العيش
and putting food on the table, raising a family,
وتوفير الطعام على المائدة، وتكوين أسرة،
writing thank you letters,
وكتابة رسائل الشكر
you have to now contend with
عليك الآن أن تتعامل مع
answering a mountain of unanswered emails,
الرد على أكوام من الرسائل الإلكترونية
updating a Facebook page,
التي لم يُرد عليها وتحديث صفحة الفيس بوك
feeding your Twitter feed.
وإضافة تغريدات جديدة على تويتر
And cloudspotting legitimizes doing nothing.
إن مشاهدة السحب تجيز لك عدم القيام بأي شيء
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And sometimes we need —
وفي بعض الأحيان نحتاج إلى –
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Sometimes we need excuses to do nothing.
أحيانًا نحتاج إلى أعذار لعدم القيام بأي شيء
We need to be reminded by these
ونحن نحتاج إلى هذه الآلهة الراعية
patron goddesses of idle fellows
للرفاق العاطلين عن العمل لتذكرنا بأن
that slowing down
تهدئة السرعة
and being in the present, not thinking about
والوجود في الحاضر دون التفكير في
what you've got to do and what you should have done,
ما يجب عليك القيام به وما كان ينبغي عليك القيام به
but just being here, letting your imagination
لكن مجرد الوجود هنا والسماح لمخيلتك
lift from the everyday concerns down here
بالابتعاد عن مخاوف الحياة اليومية الموجودة هنا بأسفل
and just being in the present, it's good for you,
ومجرد وجودك في الحاضر أمر جيد لك
and it's good for the way you feel.
وهو أمر جيد لمشاعرك
It's good for your ideas. It's good for your creativity.
وأمر جيد لأفكارك وإبداعك
It's good for your soul.
وأمر جيد لروحك
So keep looking up,
فلتستمر في النظر إلى أعلى
marvel at the ephemeral beauty,
واسمح لهذا الجمال العابر بإثارة الدهشة في نفسك
and always remember to live life with your head in the clouds.
وتذكر دائماً أن تعيش الحياة حالمًا متأملاً.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)